So the board has the responsibility to select
the CEO, encourage the CEO, advise the CEO,
evaluate the CEO's performance and give feedback accordingly,
compensate the CEO and unfortunately really also remove
the CEO where the CEO is not performing.
This is one area where many boards don't
do well because CEOs are typically tenured and
because they also wield such enormous power.
A lot of the time the CEO perhaps
can also be an owner-manager but really
and truly a board that would function and
be effective should be able to put an
erring CEO in line.
A non-performing CEO is of no use
to themselves and certainly they are of no
use to the company.
Whether or not the CEO is performing is
not a subjective decision, it's totally objective based
on the KPIs that have been set by
the board and if the CEO's performance falls
short of those KPIs then feedback should be
given and where non-performance persists then the
board should do the needful.
But before the board can do the needful
it means that the board itself has put
in place a watertight succession planning process which
includes the board knowing that there's a pipeline
to succession and the board having sufficient visibility
to the direct reports of the CEO.
So what are the elements of board effectiveness?
The structure and composition of the board, effective
use of board committees, board dynamics, we'll go
into each of this in a minute, the
board agenda, how well the board can identify
and root out dysfunctionality in its midst and
of course performance evaluation.
So in terms of structure and composition on
the board the starting point is how our
directors have been appointed.
The board has to have a formal and
rigorous process of appointing directors, that process has
to be proactive so we're not thinking of
replacing directors when they have left or when
they are giving notice that they are going
to leave the board.
Periodically the board should do a skills assessment
of its composition, what skills do we have,
what skills are lacking, what skills do we
need if we're going to move into the
future and how do we acquire those skills.
So the board will typically drop a criteria
with the kind of directors that it wants
on the board and what skills gap there
exists such that there is a transparent process
and a rigorous process like that.
It's typical these days for directors to appoint
consultants to help them in the process of
identifying suitable directors that meet the criteria that
they have set.
In terms of composition and structure of the
board, the board should have the three types
of directors that we have described, non-executive,
executive directors and dependent non-executive directors.
For better effectiveness it is recommended that as
many as the non-executives themselves should be
independent, but what is critical and paramount across
all the codes is that non-executive directors
should be majority of the board.
So in a situation where you have an
equal number of executives and non-executives it
doesn't make for a very effective board.
It is also important for the structure of
the board that the board is robustly diverse.
Diversity in this instance refers to gender, age,
ethnicity, background, experience in all the forms of
diversity as much as possible.
Increasingly we're seeing boards appointing directors from outside
of their own jurisdiction just to give that
international experience as a subset of diversity as
well.
There should be clear separation of power between
the board and management such that there's no
overlap in their duties and this overlap can
be prevented by having a clear delegation of
authority document that defines the role of the
board and defines the matters that it has
delegated to management.